all right
it's our
second discussion in cohort 4 of chapter
one
uh does anyone at the beginning want to
just bring up any comment or any
specific question about chapter one
or otherwise we have we can
look at one uh recent stream transcript
okay so Terry um you asked a question
about the generative model the
generative process so maybe just
summarize that question
and then and then we'll see how it
played out recently
uh my question was when we were trying
to create a model we create the
generative model we sort of Define it in
four
over four sort of domains and and and
then at then you define the generative
process
but my if if we you know think of the
Markov blanket as separating B
internal state from the underable
external State well if we're creating a
model
and that model depends on us creating
something that is
in fact on mobile or is there not a
corruption within that
thought process so it creates
an impression that within the context of
if I take my Markov blanket is bad my
skin
then um I uh
I cannot know what is the generative
process so there's got to be some flaw
in our system of modeling if it depends
on creating something we can't do
all right awesome and uh when you when
you asked that it made me think of the
recent
um
stream with Maxwell ramstead now
operation and Ali and others
and uh
this highlighted a uh inconsistency in
the generative model generative process
uh topic Ollie do you want to summarize
um
what you what you asked and and what
they wrote or said
yeah of course uh well uh we were
talking about uh the I mean discrepancy
between Maxwell's presentation and also
the recent paper because uh in figure
one in inner screen paper uh they've
indicated generative model as
encompassing the whole shebang I mean
encompassing the internal States the
external States and of course the
blanket States so
um nowhere generative process was
visible in this diagram so we were
discussing with Daniel Sanjeev and
others where exactly uh General to
process can be manifested uh in this
diagram so I basically asked this this
question where is the generative process
in this diagram and uh surprisingly
Maxwell uh somehow
disowned the earlier literature and
generative process and basically uh I
mean uh he he he just I mean interpreted
the generative model in a kind of new
more sophisticated way that wouldn't
require any separate entity as
generative process because General to
model basically
includes the joint probability of every
possible of uh every everything that
markup blankets
um uh I mean partitions so it it is a
joint probability of internal States
blanket States and the external States
uh but on the other hand
when we want to uh model a situation and
not just I mean describe a physical
phenomena or a physical system then of
course we can Define our own generative
model as something
or let's put it this way as
kind of dynamics that we expect
the system or the situation
the situation we have to follow those
Dynamics and so for instance if we want
to model a very simple linear behavior
of a I don't know mechanical system then
of course the Newtonian mechanics or you
know the terms the lagrangian mechanics
of the system can constitute the
generative process of the system so uh
yeah that's uh basically the uh
gist of Maxwell's argument uh at least
as far as I understand it
quite a discussion
we can kind of parse it out better but
the transcripts out there like
so
um as with everything in the textbook
it's sort of like there's a there's some
internal ontology
and then
um it's somehow aligned with the broader
active Gestalt and for that
you will still it helps to understand
the generating process and the particles
of the agents and so um like to to the
to to the earlier question how can you
model the unknown because you're
modeling something into existence in the
act of modeling
so you can have the real temperature of
the room do statistics on an unobserved
that maps to the observables so in
practice there's no issue but then
people have a lot of
um degrees of interpretation with what
that means and that's the whole and what
that means for different situations
but all that aside in terms of
these two ways to talk about generative
model generative process
[Music]
um
as it's being shown in the inner screen
paper the generative models just the
entire process giving rise to 100 of the
system's level description
including states that generate other
observables
whereas in the textbook they go to some
length and distinction to highlight
the generative model
which has an aboutness of a generative
process
the underlying particular partition
like separating it this way is not
changed
so it's the same topology of the of the
underlying
graph that gives rise to all the
you know formalisms
but it's just kind of it's a truly a
nomenclature question
about where you say okay now these it's
like what yeah
it's just nomenclature question about
describing this
but it's one that always comes up
so
what does anyone think about this it's
kind of a funny random but cool ongoing
topic
uh sorry if I may add uh some additional
comments to what I've just previously
said I mean to my mind this recent
interpretation actually uh makes more
sense because uh one of the
misconceptions around fep uh has always
been how I mean how can we sure about
how to model generative process if the
causes of the observables are as the
name suggests latent States or hidden
States right so if we don't know uh the
exact causes of those observations how
is it possible to model it in a precise
probabilistic
probabilistic terms but in this new way
of uh looking at the generative model
versus generative process well we can
basically I mean somehow
put this issue under the Rock by by
somehow reinterpreting the generative
model as uh including both the external
States and the internal States and only
account and only following the
variational density of the internal
States as
I mean tracing or tracking or not
tracking the external States so that's
basically uh I mean the whole thing the
whole model and and its whole relation
with the quote-unquote reality is
something uh more akin to probably an
instrumentalist
view of reality rather than
I mean the realest uh the uh perspective
because uh here we just used this
theoretical framework only to account
for the parts of the reality or the
behavior with the reality that we can
model
it it looks like Alexa tautology but
that's basically what I understood by
this
a new interpretation uh so that's I am
probably one of the ways to evade those
uh criticisms or misconceptions around
the generative process
thank you Ali very interesting
just to kind of connect this to a
previous discussion in live stream six
one of the early paper-based discussions
this was like described as the tale of
two densities and we probably even use
this meme
still
um but the tale of two densities was the
generative direction from the
temperature in the room hidden State
emitting thermometer readings was the
generative model
a generative Direction it's referring to
the same graph still and the recognition
density was like from the sensor data
the incoming
and so that led to a lot of um well like
okay the generative is action the
recognition sensory
and uh I think what Ali is pointing to
is that
um
if you just kind of say uh well even if
it has a million nodes
whether one's internal external blanket
is relative to whichever one you're
talking about so those are not absolute
States
so you might as well just call the whole
thing a generative model
still with certain uh components whose
sparseness gives them certain properties
but there's no need to necessarily
distinguish
between these two
um but still it makes sense to think
take it think about an agent-based
modeling perspective and about the
process that generates so so it's not
that it invalidates what the textbook
says just from a first thought
it's it just sort of expands the scope
of what people will probably mean with
generative model which is just to say
the whole generating architecture of the
program probably also closer with
generative AI so it's it's
um probably a good direction to go
but it will still but but this could be
thought of as just like agent and Niche
well can I yeah yeah this could be a
problem about for me about using
language right so whenever you say there
is a temperature in the hidden external
state
when you say temperature that's a
perception uh you know we can think of
it as a representative of the amount of
energy in that external State and we
perceive it as a core layer of heat uh
so so but but actually we we kind of no
idea what that what that what that is we
use this term temperature uh oh but we
don't know what that means inter if you
think of that you know like the the
physics of information Pro or physics is
information process and so that the
temperature is information that exists
in the all knowable external State we
our perception of temperature is
actually part of the electromagnetic
spectrum you know the
um infrared light is what were is what
we detect as temperature and then we
call we we call it a thing in the x or
we may wait for we we make an assumption
about what that means in the external
state but really I I kind of think that
we uh our our quality of temperature
isn't what we mean when we measure the
temperature
of the external state with a thermometer
or a temperature receptor in our skin
you know so I again I always feel like
I'm talking like I've taken too many
drugs and I'm a 14 year old but you you
know it it
cut this this kind of
um
it feels like there are loads of like
syntaxers in the thought processes
around all this so I'm I'm and
um it it it confuses me
Lexi yeah I was had a perspective on
this question please bear with me if it
sounds a little too simplistic and you
know think about it this way you know
I'm quoting Mark songs by the way if my
body is immersed in an environment with
you know 70 degrees uh Celsius
temperature and I don't solve that
problem I die
if my body is immersed in the
environment with zero degrees Celsius
and I don't solve that problem I die so
at some point it is not about complex
philosophical things because you can go
into physics originally temperature and
entropy were variables designed for a
system at equilibrium
so we can get as semantically complex as
you like but again taken back to bodies
you know there is that very specific
thing that if you you know are outside
of the homeostatic range of temperatures
and you do not solve that problem
originally through reflexes through
sweating or whatever and maybe through
Behavior if you don't solve it you die
so how is that for the you know
temperature is that okay
yeah but just one point on temperature I
think you you
um it's a great question and you you are
indicating like sort of the real
ontological base existence reality which
of course even people have different
views on that but you can model the
unobserved state as like we could say
this is the the
um the SAT score
but we're not fully observing it because
we we have a partially ripped up file so
the modeling of what is a hidden State
versus an observable is really just a
question of like what do you have data
for or want it and then what do you want
to include as a causal or latent factor
in your model but you don't necessarily
have data for as an observable
but you may even choose to have hidden
States for things that you could get
data for
so I think that's the kind of
deflationary bent in this textbook and
and maybe in many people's active
inference Journeys when the model itself
is built as they encourage people to do
from the first chapter to the last
then you see the specifics of how it
plays out in that generative model and
the contributions to the field consist
of specific generative models made
and general claims with the active
inference ontology
the thing
um that it struck me is to in order to
act in the world to remove myself from
the temperature that's going to burn my
skin I don't actually have to know
anything about the generative process I
can make assumptions about the
generative process and then act in the
world to try to alter that but my my
confusion lies with how we can then
within model construction
dictate what the process what the
generative process is and I can
understand why you have to do that if
you've got to create a model but it kind
of just doesn't speak to
the
to the the ideas laid out in chapter one
in this book you know that's that's
another angle is uh when you approach a
specific question or a line of inquiry
you're not trying to make the the total
um twin through a scientific model
you could learn something about the knee
without having the full
simulation whatever that would even mean
of a knee
so
I
in the specific modeling but maybe
that's coming from an experimentalist's
perspective so I'm not sure Alexi
yeah I I had I had maybe in a reaction
but I wonder if maybe we need to maybe
time to maybe let this idea sink is it
appropriate for me to ask another
question on a slightly different topic
or would that be too abruptly yeah
definitely that sounds totally good if
you are if it's here or just ask it so
it's about chapter one and the uh I'm
reacting to this text action is
quintessentially goal directed and
purposive
okay so
um I understand that you know there's a
goal to stay alive no questions right
but you know if we move to human
subjects and you know uh uh uh please
forgive me sort of Clinical Psychology
Psychotherapy and there's a ton of
action that humans do that at least
doesn't appear as gold directed or
pervasive in fact if every action humans
did was goal directed and purpose if we
wouldn't need Psychotherapy at all
like we have I don't know
um
maladaptive behaviors we have obsessions
compulsions ticks and whatnot so uh I'm
not exactly sure if we stand with that
postula that every action is going to
essentially goal directed and pervasive
would that model not oversimplify things
for human subjects
that's a great question a short thought
on it and then anyone can raise their
hand is
even an isocade can be purposeful
purposive because you can explain it in
terms of using this framework so it
doesn't necessarily mean that in some
integrated way it's beneficial for the
person's life or for any given social
recognition or bodily Health necessarily
because you can do modeling of
pathologies too but the purposiveness is
just local teleology local directedness
moving the elbow from one to to do a
slot machine again and again is
purposive you can argue whether it is
with the person's long-term professional
interest but the action is still
proposive
yeah well my my issue with the
teleological explanation is that it is
often uh very speculative when people
for example tell me that my state of
depression has a purpose to inform me
that I have an unmet need which is
mainstream you know models and Clinical
Psychology sometimes like how do you
know that depression doesn't have five
different purposes and models we pretty
much you know if you if you say in first
speculate that that's the the purpose of
depression so the teleology is is a
little kind of weird for me maybe it is
mainstream and active inference
framework but it's a little weird yeah
but maybe I'll think about it more a
related question is this when we say the
goal directed character of action the
question is whose goal again going back
to human subjects there's conscious
there's unconscious processes and
sometimes people do something and
they're like I did this thing I
rationally know I shouldn't have done it
but I did it anyway
which suggests that they have multiple
components of their agency and not just
you know a unitary John who you know
decided all the goals and purposes so
the question is whose goals what what
exactly do we assume unitarity do you
assume that the agent is a singular
thing
yeah great question Kate
well my thoughts on this are that
um I would say that in my understanding
at least
um
active inference views the Mind as a
hierarchical structure but definitely
hierarchical buildup or many different
um
sub layers of the brain and ultimately
the goal of therapy like in some random
therapist but in some way it could be
the integration of all these different
sounds but those in by themselves the
lower lower levels or lower parts of the
hierarchical components of the hierarchy
within their own domain they are
purposing action the action within those
domains they don't they don't solve the
host necessarily as such but within
their own logic internal logic even if
you could put it in the math it would
fit the free energy principle and the
active influence so the goal there is to
figure out how to bring the hierarchy
together in a more purposive or healthy
way that's that that's the thought that
your comment triggered Alexi that's all
I have to say about that I I'm very much
for this thought and it's beautiful
except you know bear with me maybe I'm a
devil's advocate but what I see in
clinical work and what is mainstream and
psychodynamic Psychotherapy is mental
conflicts such as I want this
but I cannot have it or I I should be
doing this but I want to do something
else or I Want A and B and they're
mutually exclusive and in that regard
there is no hierarchy there is an
unresolved conflict mind and a conflict
is very mainstream kind of 100 year old
clinical tradition and you know
ultimately you don't resolve those
things you know that that mind goes from
one conflict to another to the third one
we have multiple needs like the Famous
Madonna syndrome is an example of
that and how people find a compromise
from that is a sort of personality so I
I just do think that some of these
assumptions and postulates we make early
on that there's this you know either
it's resolved through the hierarchy or
there's a singular agent whose goals and
purposes we follow are you know okay for
for a bacteria but maybe not for human
mind
well but um card Horace Harris
um his studies on psychedelics
and the um his theory of how the
psychedelics would kind of reset the
priors reset the Precision of the priors
the villains and in many cases it
oftentimes helps with some of the
symptoms which would argue for that view
so you may not be able to do it verbally
through a verbal interaction or through
language but in some other you know
parts of it may be open to more chemical
or you know
neural transmitter
kind of related reset as opposed to a
verbal reset
but anyway
just just to kind of
um give it one thought and then ali
um goal is not really a required term
just my personal view in the active
inference ontology we don't talk about
kicking a ball through a goal we don't
talk about a milestone based goal it's
it doesn't come up when we're actually
using the active infantology it's not a
parameter in the model
but cybernetics has long been antilios
and all these debates so I think
actually what's really exciting and I'll
say here for now is it actually points
towards exciting different ways of
understanding purpose of behavior
and where goals and rewards come into
play by thinking about likely paths
being selected
rather than rewarding paths and how that
generalizes across a system that stays
in a wooden Groove and how that also May
relate to these higher order
sophisticated cognitive functions like
narrative but that is not something that
we're going to see in figure 4.3 that's
something where once you build that
Tower of Babel then you'll know but
hypothetically what can you say without
the generative model of what people are
talking about because we're not talking
about just the base four nodes modeling
the whole brain like that if you were
going to make a model that had multiple
debating personalities then it simply
would have that feature
Ollie
well actually I think uh the term action
here
is used
um instead of in I mean to refer to
intentional action
so I I don't think it's action in its
broadest sense but even if uh even if we
restrict ourselves to only intentional
actions there are some theories both
philosophical and in cognitive science
uh that tries to somehow
frame this notion of action in terms of
an alternative
conception of causality so one notable
work in that regard is the work of
Alicia
in her work in her book Dynamics and
actions so in this book I mean the basic
premise of this book is exactly uh the
question what is the difference between
a wink and a blink right so uh
I mean in order to come in order to
come up with a viable theory of action
that that can
include all of these uh intentional and
non-intentional actions uh she proposes
a theory of causation based not on uh
traditional linear cause and effects but
rather
[Music]
looking at the whole complex adaptive
system as
um as as possessing some constraints and
looking at those constraints as uh
as as somehow giving rise to causation
so you know the words the what we mean
by causation uh is actually
undertaken by those constraints of those
uh complex adaptive systems
sorry so these dynamical constraints uh
can actually
account for both bottom-up and top down
causal relations
so in this sense it can include both
intentional action and non-intentional
action and if we take goal-directed
action as uh kinds of action that tries
to satisfy those dynamical constraints
then this
um I mean claim in the book can make
sense in this
complex dynamical system framework
great thank you Lexi
I just had a couple reactions uh Daniel
to what you said and thank you for your
comment about gold being necessary or
not please forgive me if my metaphors
are very simplistic so the car sitting
in the parking lot idling burning gas
is increasing entropy it is uh not
moving anywhere right a car going to
where I needed to go is going toward a
goal and perhaps it is wasting some
energy and as well so if we remove the
goal out then you know how will we
actually look at the free energy versus
you know the energy used toward a
meaningful purpose you know so I think
implicitly perhaps a goal like the goal
is to survive for an organism and to
maintain survival evolutionarily survive
until reproductive agent reproduce you
know some kind of goals like that exist
perhaps you know if you take all of them
out then then it's all entropy right and
also had a maybe reaction to Kate that
you know I am very very respectful of
Cartwright Harris's work and
psychedelics with that I just I'm highly
skeptical of the idea of reset or
anything brief because you know
attachment style in a human being takes
from 8 to 66 to uh 18 months you know
nine women pregnant for a month will not
produce a baby you know personality
takes time to form and all of this sort
of quick you know uh resets whether it's
Ayahuasca or ketamine or even
electroconvulsive therapy I just don't
buy that you know I think that that it's
minded and conflict remains in a
conflict it just how it solves the
conflict is is the question it may be
solving it more adaptively more you know
in a more nuanced way but I don't think
that anything quick like a magic wand of
psychedelics will will resolve that in
any way so
yeah one paper by Adam saffron is the
Albus model so while that relaxation of
beliefs was more visible
and led to a kind of
um relaxation based emphasis on what
psychedelics might do which may be half
the picture
um Adam just kind of generalized it to
altering like well depending on which
generative model you make or how you
think about what the brain is or
whatever
um different
um pharmaceutical or non-pharmaceutical
experiences are going to not just purely
relax a distribution because the
distributions are part of the map
so I think
um like
it it's not a property the physical
molecule to do so except again
interpreted in this more abstract causal
space
um
to your question Alexi
you know you talk about a car in the
parking lot it's great it's just
disordering material and it's not going
anywhere it's not goal oriented but
its purpose could be described hyper
locally as just being in one place like
a rock's purpose just using again this
broader concept of purpose which doesn't
come up in the acting phonology we don't
need the goal but the Rock's goal is
just to be right there the Leaf's goal
is to go Downstream so by having a
deflationary optional concept of
intentional Behavior
including um like Carl first
um wood lice example
where there was insects running around
on the pavement and they went faster
where it was light and slower it was
dark
so they accumulated where it was dark
so including a whole Continuum of
intentionality
based upon return to an attracting set
is it just turns out to be enormously
General
now how to connect that to the the
physical entropy lost by organisms open
question
and then how to use some other
um terms from thermodynamics like what
would informational work be versus
informational Heat
well Chris Fields is certainly
approaching those types of questions but
um
I hope that addresses a few pieces of it
something doing the most likely thing
is exactly the Criterion that you would
use first for statistics
and so in that way it's why we can use
statistics so
um adeptly in this modeling
because statistics isn't about simply
maximizing reward but like all
statistics is about finding
um this path of least action in an
informational space Ali
sorry it was my hand risen from before
sorry oh no worries
anyone who hasn't uh brought something
up just definitely has gone all over
which is totally
cool but if somebody wants to go to a
specific question of chapter one or a
quote we could do that
um I did want to chime in on the
the previous topic about
um
action is quintessentially goal directed
and Professor uh
so I mean you know we have some ways to
get further into the textbook but I mean
we're going to be going over things like
policy selection kind of like I'm
assuming active inference involves not
just settling upon a single unchanging
policy right continuing with that that's
what an agent operates with rather it
would be you know potential entire
series of competing policies that may
very well be actively updated based upon
what the agent has maybe learned in the
past new incoming observations so I'm
just kind of reflecting on everything
that's been said and
um because whenever I read this I I
would it feels a little bit easier for
me to take uh the phrase goal directed
with a bit of a grain of salt and think
like oh there could be multiple
potentially even conflicting policies in
play that themselves are constantly
potentially changing or shifting a
variety of ways so just yeah it's just a
kind of final comment they supposed on
that topic I was thinking about yeah
that's awesome it's it's so true policy
is evaluated every time steps so this is
exactly how we integrate
action into the loop whether like ooda
Loop or just behavioral uh loop so
that's a great point
Terry
and just uh the way I interpreted that
was that the goal isn't uh that the goal
is fundamentally to
um answer questions of the universe and
uh therefore
uh
get evidence that then can be fed into
the variational free energy model
uh to either update or prioritize or act
in the world to
um
to reduce the variational free energy so
the goal isn't
a goal to achieve an end the goal the
end is to
answer the question about
uh
minimizing variational free energy
and then our behavior in the world that
we read as
policy LED goal directed is actually
more a function of that primary
objective of the organism which is to
minimize variational free energy
great points
again I'd highlight that we can Model A
baseball on a parabola as doing the most
likely thing we could identify a
radioactive isotope that's
probabilistically emitting things over a
given time window as doing the most
expected thing
so a lot can get brought into statistics
which does breed this whole fascinating
area of like map territory type
distinctions
so suffice to say action is going to be
totally integrated into this model
enabling a lot of interpretations
as the recent literature Witnesses Lexi
thank you so much Daniel I was just yeah
thinking about everyone everybody said
but I think your word intentionality
connected it from me and maybe the issue
that I have please forgive me is lexical
because so in my world you know
intentionality is required the the
sentence you said that Rock's goal is to
stay in place is an oxymoron and and
sort of psychology because you can only
have a goal if you have a mind
so in that regard bacteria that moves
toward the like you know gradient of the
food and withdraws from Pain does not
have a goal and a purpose because it
ain't got a mind so that that maybe is a
different use of language and if they
use the word gold here in a sense that
the Rock's goal is to stay in place it's
an attribution I would perhaps it's an
unfortunate use of a term but maybe we
can say It's You Know The Rock's
Dynamics started to stay in place but it
doesn't have any goals you know there's
no mind there there's no agent there's
no agent capable of choosing a versus B
in Iraq yeah
I I I totally agree like it is sort of a
in a narrow and a broad sense sometimes
there's going to be like gray area
assignment just like um well this enzyme
wants to bind to this one
I've heard it a thousand times so it's
like but it's not intended as a
reflexive
you know statement about the protein
being a strange Loop maybe it's below
some level of critical ability
but we can model this all in an
integrated fashion
so we can still model the game theory of
something that we don't even think plays
it implicit
representational game
that's why there's this whole
representationalist debate and then we
can do all these kinds of modeling links
really composably which is kind of the
exciting piece which is also why the the
kernel
ultimately what we're working towards
like figure 4.3 these generative models
the kernels vary
it's it's not applicable to any given
situation except a purely purely
pedagogical
and it's extremely sparse on
commitments
because it's basically of the same type
as every other statistical model in
Bayesian statistics
so it's not like an esoteric type of
model
but it opens many questions that I think
again we see every day which is really
exciting and part of the fun and and why
many people can contribute in as well
but there's just so many interesting
angles to it and I think also sanjeev's
textbook
that um is in progress with several of
you um here who who may be um in that
group like
that there's a whole statistics degree
slash
undergraduate or Beyond leading up to
a lot of things that really help set the
stage
and and his his work I I think will be
like for people who want to see that
level of depth
and then meanwhile understanding what
other
um fun paths and ways are there in this
whole
work because certainly it's always every
sentence you could be like
what is happening and uh you know if
this word meant that and if this person
was defining it this way
so certainly finding a path on through
and like what's the claim
when a lot of it is internally
referential
um
however that's part of its coherence and
consistency
and those the but sometimes the evidence
for the consistency is a little bit hard
to
convey because these are relatively
recent
understandings
hopefully that's just like a little
context
foreign
anyone else have a thought or a question
on
chapter one Terry or than anyone else
and
it's it's relevant to this thing about
that a rock has no mind but a rock guy
is you know maybe over longer time
scales to sustain itself as a rock it
has to uh
minimize its free energy in terms of its
uh interactions with the external State
and whenever the uh variational free
energy within that system Alters it will
never be oxidize or you know get broken
up or if they think you know it it can't
act in the world to maintain its
variational free energy at a minimum but
it still has to maintain that
variational free energy at a minimum and
when it can't it changes to something
else so you know the notion that because
that that that
um
you know all objects and in the world
sustain themselves and they're not in in
the state that they are currently in by
minimizing variational free energy
whether you're a tree a human a rock or
a you know a Galaxy probably
um uh I I what's your reaction to that
because I I know that we we you know
they reference
like trees aren't can't do things but
trees do communicate with each other you
know as we and and I suppose I was
obstruct by this concept of pan psychism
that exists within you know the sort of
the the the thinkers in in in in in in
the nature of Consciousness I'm just
interested
yeah it's it's something that's
stimulated by what Alexi said and I'm
interested in what you have to say about
that
yeah
it's very it's interesting I mean it's
certainly interesting areas you brought
up and the way that there could be a
kind of deflationary account
where just it's pan cognitivist
or just pan computationalists but then
people debate what's a computer and they
say well it's pancognitivist but then
they debate what is cognition is the
baseball Computing and it's the water
Computing where it expects to be
downhill so those are all the debates
but
most of us
um
see a world with dense but sparse
connectivities
so
it sometimes it's like a lot of problem
admiration which can be a good thing
but um pointing to communication
Pathways amongst living things
is only surprising in light of extremely
recent specific scientific observations
so but I'm I'm not sure I mean that's
there's so many other areas you brought
up in the Consciousness and I mean these
are all the huge
questions Ali
uh yeah again uh one of the other common
misconceptions about fep is that some
people think fep as providing a kind of
ontological conditions for existence or
at least persistence through time
but actually what fep claims is that if
something exists it must have properties
that look as if they follow the path of
least action so it's the other way
around fpp doesn't provide any
conditions for the Existence or
persistent through time at all but it
rather I mean if we take the persistence
or the existence as the basic premise of
our argument then we can
and follow that by consider by
describing the behavior of uh of the
phenomena or or the system by describing
uh the
um I mean trajectories of their
variational density uh in terms of uh
least action principle so uh I think
this is one of the things that people uh
some sometimes
criticize fep as something that I mean
of course it's
claimed to be theory of every thing but
it's not something as some ontological
or metaphysical
theory for anything it just tries to
describe I mean beginning from the
ontological existence it tries to
describe the ensuing characteristic six
of the systems that persist through time
and in particular
highly complex
high-dimensional self-organizing systems
amazing points Ali thank you
the condition of modeling something
is to have these properties every
measurement that's that's if it's static
it's it's uh with its movement is within
the measurement the classical limit
if it's so Dynamic it's moving faster
than the time scale measurement you just
get basically uninformative signal so we
always kind of tuned in Bucky Fuller
zone of modeling Proxima modeling which
we can extend with microscopes uh
telescopes
um that's one way to look at this that's
a kind of like scientific realism
approach
but then for things that you can't or
didn't model you have hidden States
so ultimately you have it covered
um but then this is really the the
inversion of the um ontological theories
of everything that this is how it really
is this is how it is out there
um this is how the metaphysics are that
you know project our world a certain way
that is like why ontology is the
philosophy of what is
however if we precondition upon
existence someone will look at an and
wanted to go off the trail there it's
like
but you have the whole evolutionary
history that sets up its decision making
so maybe the purposiveness of that you
might have a super deflationary response
um but again whatever level of
sophistication the thing is from
essentially inert
or totally inert to repetitive motion to
sophisticated motion
that can be understood by an observer as
a path of least action
as they do statistics
so in that sense it licenses little more
metaphysics than a linear regression
as an analytic method
then I think again there's so many
interesting angles why it has been
um discussed in all of these more
philosophical contexts
um
because reductionism isn't the whole
picture
so the theory in itself or any given
theory in itself might not take on all
these accounts
and there may just be tangled webs of
perspectives and and difference
languaging and uh different applications
around some of these topics
but it is fun and fast when it's small
and the few people's perspectives are
essentially knowable
and there are
um always new information coming in
literally through these funny modern
channels and hearing what Maxwell and
Carl at all think Andrew
yeah yeah I just uh just my two cents
there is that um
you know I find the pan cognitive stuff
um rather interesting than that said I
personally came to active inference
because I'm interested in its
application to uh living systems and
especially human beings and so the brain
uh from a neuroscience perspective but
also how it might be applied
and working with psychopathologies
treatments and so on and so
um I think so far I'm just viewing it in
more pragmatic sense of like how can we
use this in the same way that I also
work as a data scientist and so I don't
view everything as a gradient boosting
machine but I will attempt to apply a
model to a situation to see if I can
get anything useful out of it right so
that's that's kind of how I've taken
this so far I mean I've read some really
fascinating papers you know one by a
psychiatrist who applied active
inference to uh post-traumatic stress
disorder described um hyper precise
priors in the upper cortical regions is
like you know someone who experiences
reliving the
um excuse me that can be triggered by a
certain phenomena that kind of spark or
activate those those previous priors
that gets superimposed on the incoming
sensory observations even though it's
inaccurate
um so that's I mean
I'm personally a little less concerned
with the Precision of ontological claims
and so on but um but but kind of
how this can help us to reinterpret
different kinds of phenomena and from
there maybe use it like for good for
some kind of useful purpose and sounds
really it's really fascinating you know
so it's
awesome thank you for sharing that
yeah
it is very interesting
anyone else want to just give a comment
in the last
minutes
or otherwise we will be
um
going into chapter two
chapter two is gonna be uh
another two weeks
we can look at the figure and look at
the high road and low road again just
kind of look ahead
low road
and the high road
chapter 2 and chapter three that will be
the coming month
also some people
um
have asked about the
math learning group
so
I I made a little comment thread if you
just comment on this thread then I think
people who want to do a certain kind of
work can maybe find each other this way
and it can be in the Discord or a gypsy
link or however people prefer
um
and uh
yeah continue to to check out and
comment or or improve if you want any of
the AI
math things as we head into chapter two
um
explore which of these equations if you
can evaluate which one of these AI
explanations or make comments on them
some are useful some are not so
you know
but I hope there's a lot of fun things
we can do in the coming
weeks chapter 2 is definitely going to
get into it because it just starts the
real non-introduction part of the book
um
but yeah does anyone have any other
thoughts or questions or anyone who's
read chapter two before
Wanna Give a teaser
or or
Ali go for it
well yeah actually chapter two is where
the real fun begins I mean after
the introductory chapter and now we're
uh into the real set of things by
considering the two of the most Central
equations of active inference namely
equations 2.5 and 2.6 one for
variational free energy the other four
expected free energy which will come to
time and time again throughout the whole
book
so it's probably one of the most
fundamentally important chapters
uh
great comments anyone else want to add
anything
okay
all right thank you all see you around
bye